[music]
At an antique store in London, a
remarkable discovery has been made that
has thrown light on the bloody end of
the Zars of Russia and the birth of the
Soviet Union.
>> Well, it was a a miracle. We were here
at Wartsky and in through that very door
behind you walked a gentleman. [music]
He was the most unassuming,
unprepossessing individual, but in his
hands he had a sheath of photographs.
This mysterious stranger had pictures of
a lost treasure made by the legendary
Carl Faber. A master jeweler and
favorite of the Russian Imperial [music]
Court.
Like the Romanovs, Faber himself would
ultimately be a victim of the terrifying
Russian Revolution. And one of his
greatest creations would go missing for
a century, having to survive two world
wars and a precarious trip to America
before pictures of it finally made their
way to London.
This has been the target of [music] our
dreams for so long that I recognized it
instantaneously. But of course, as an
[music] antique dealer, your first
reaction is no. You doubt everything.
But looking at the images and then
looking at him, it had to be true.
50 Imperial Faber eggs are known to have
been made. Could one of the missing ones
have finally been found? Of course, we
couldn't confirm that until we had
handled the object itself.
St. Petersburg, Russia. It was in 1917
in this elegant city on the Baltic Sea
that the story of the K Faber company
and their legendary Imperial eggs came
to a crashing end.
>> This where you made them.
>> The workshops downstairs
we design
we used to design our products in here.
The eggs,
>> not just commissions from his majesty.
>> Citizen Romangh,
>> citizen Romanov,
>> it's a time capsule. It's a it's a
portal. I mean, we in Russian history,
we have this false line of 1917. And
each and every one of these pieces
[music] catapults us back to that time
when there were beautiful Grand
Duchesses, a hemophiliac heir, a
mystical Rasputin, and all of these
people who were annihilated. I saw them
once.
>> The eggs.
I was a boy.
My grandfather took me to your
exhibition.
>> Each one of these [music] pieces tie us
back to an aristocracy, um a religion, a
system of uh governing. [music] That's
that's absolutely gone. And they're the
only tangible evidence that these people
ever lived.
>> He was our bloody Sunday.
Your friend's Imperial Guard shot him
right here.
He was just an old man.
I wish I'd smashed the eggs when I'd had
the chance.
>> So, how had it all gone so horribly
wrong for Faber and the aristocracy that
adored him? And just what happened to
the Faber eggs? The story begins in the
same city where it ended, St.
Petersburg.
The Fabe family originally came out from
France. They were refugees from the um
repeal of the edict of Nance. [music]
That's to say they were hugenos
protestants being persecuted by Louis
the 14th and they fled eastwards from
there. Carl Fabraier known sometimes as
Peter Carl because he was christened
that born in 1846 schooled in [music]
the German school in St. Petersburg.
>> His father owned a small jewelry shop.
It was a small jewelry shop but in a
smart area. His father clearly had an
eye for Carl becoming something greater
than just the jeweler he had been.
>> Fab had such [music] extraordinary
talent uh and his workshop was so
extraordinary. The other thing is that
he could be considered a foreign citizen
but being foreign in St. Petersburg was
not at [music] all unusual. It was a
very very cosmopolitan city.
>> He very much planned his education to
give him an exposure to western art to
some of the great jewelry treasures
around Europe.
>> The training that he uh received when he
was abroad with his family studying the
uh collections of [music] uh museums in
Paris and London and returns to Russia
and at the tender age of 26 takes over
his father's firm. In Russia at the end
of the 19th century though, one had to
get the attention of the Zar to really
make a name for yourself. And that was
especially the case at the time of the
autocratic Alexander III. Alexander III
was so horrified by his own father who
was generally a liberal and a
progressive that he he decided to
reverse every reform. On the other hand,
there was quite a lot to be said for
Alexander III. He was almost the only
Russian leader never to declare war on
another country. He was also an
extremely brave and powerful man.
Perhaps his major mistake [music] was
not preparing his son Nicholas II to
rule. K Faber implemented a plan that
would eventually catch the eye of this
imperious SAR. He started working on
restoring ancient Cyian jewelry which
had recently been excavated from the
Black Sea. He works on a volunteer basis
at the Amitage appraising and repairing
uh objects uh without invoicing the
court.
>> And it all really paid off for him. In
1882, there was an exhibition of Russian
art which Faber exhibited and what he
was exhibiting was pieces [music]
derived from those Cythian artifacts uh
which appealed hugely to the Russian
public because they gave the impression
that Russia had this artri prehistory uh
to compete with anything in the west.
[music] That exhibition was visited by
the Russian royal family and the Zarina
Marif Federovna bought the Zar a pair of
cufflings from the Faber stand [music]
cufflings with a cicada um motif. So
that [music] was the first uh time he
sold something to the Russian royal
family.
>> This brings him favor because in 1885
he's awarded the imperial warrant.
Having been awarded the coveted imperial
warrant, KL Faber starts work on what
would be the beginning of a long line of
Easter gifts, the first hen egg.
>> The first imperial egg was presented in
1885 by the Zar Alexander III to his
wife Marovna.
>> It's a deceptively simple egg and I
think it's a great microcosm of what
Fabrichet does so well. It's um white
enamel on the outside. It's a gold uh
yolk on the inside represented a
chicken.
>> You open it up. Inside it you find a
golden yolk. You can open up the yolk
and inside that you find a golden hen.
Inside was an imperial crown and a
pendant. So it was it was like it was
like a matrica, you know, one of these
Russian dolls. He was probably wanting
something to delight her, [music]
something to amuse her.
>> What better way to celebrate 20 years of
marriage and Easter in one um and led to
a commission, an ongoing rolling
commission that [music] lasted uh 33
years. Clearly that first egg worked and
each year the emperor would give the
empress an Easter egg from Faber.
Famously Faber started to get total
autonomy in the designs and uh with only
three commands that each gift should be
egg-shaped that each one should be
different from any predecessor and that
each one should contain something of a
surprise something that would delight
the empress. Carl Faber would quickly
become a favorite of the Russian royal
family. But neither they nor he saw the
huge changes [music] which were coming
to the Russian Empire that would leave
both Faber and his incredible imperial
eggs in great peril.
Towards the end of the 19th century,
master jeweler Carl Faber had become a
firm favorite of the Russian Zar
Alexander III and his wife, the Zarina
Marie Fiorodna. His one-of-a-kind
imperial eggs had become a highlight of
the Easter celebration.
In 1890, he presented the exquisite
Danish palaces egg, complete with a
surprise of folding miniatures.
This was followed by the memory of Azov
Egg, which commemorated a voyage taken
by the future Zar Nicholas II on the
armored Russian cruiser, the Azov, where
he narrowly survived an assassination
attempt in Japan.
The diamond trellis egg made from pale
jadeite was presented in 1892
and was followed by the caucus' egg of
translucent ruby enamel in 1893.
The Renaissance egg of 1894 would prove
to be the last presented by Zar
Alexander III to his wife Marie. That
same year, the Zar suddenly fell ill
with an incurable kidney disease and he
died at the age of only 49.
The sudden death of Thesar left his son,
the terribly unprepared Nicholas II,
[music]
to take the throne. And things got off
to a dreadful start when at a
celebration of his coronation at Kadinka
Fields near Moscow, a stampede [music]
killed over,300 people. The public at
large was not impressed with Nicholas's
[music]
response to the tragedy.
>> He was doomed after the Kadinka Fields
[music] catastrophe. He wasn't strong
like his father. He wasn't expecting to
be Sar. He was [music] only in his
20ies. He had kept a iron grasp on the
people. And then [music] um Nicholas
comes along and he's a bit more
diffident.
>> To begin your coronation with a mass
death of the population is bad. And
[music] then worse still he should go to
a ball at the French embassy on the same
day of this disaster. So that uh in fact
would did [music] his prestige an
enormous damage in which he never
recovered.
>> His strength and his weakness was that
he was uh slightly normal and he he
rather liked normal life. He liked
chopping wood, being with his family and
uh smoking [music] which he did a lot of
the time. Fortunately for Faber though,
Nicholas [music] continued the tradition
of imperial Easter eggs. And in fact,
two were now requested each year. One
for Nicholas's mother, the now Daaja
Empress, and one for the new Zarina
Alexandra, who unfortunately was just as
unpopular as the Zar.
>> Sarina Alexandra came from the small
German court of Dharmstat. And uh she
was known as the German one. That was a
problem for her to get over to start
with.
>> Some Russian empresses have overcome
this. But she was extremely tactless.
She was convinced that Russia should be
an absolute monarchy and she pushed her
husband and she had extremely bad
judgment.
>> She didn't enjoy balls and dances. Uh
she thought that the Russian aristocracy
were very decadent. Meanwhile, the
daagger had been very fun-loving and was
very popular. that the Tsarina had a
hard act to follow and she didn't really
manage.
>> The first pair of eggs given was in 1895
when Zarina Alexandra received the rose
bud egg and the daager received the blue
serpent clock egg. This egg would
eventually end up in Monaco where it
became a treasured possession of
Princess Grace.
>> Queen Elizabeth and Prince Philillip
take the royal drive along the superb
[music] course. Princess Grace and
Prince Reneier are guests. Three other
eggs also ended up in royal possession
becoming the property of Queen Elizabeth
II. The colonade egg, the basket of
flowers egg, and the stunning mosaic
egg. It seems that Faber has always been
a favorite [music] of royalty right from
the days of his very first royal client,
the Daaja Empress, Marie Fiorodna.
>> Christ is risen.
>> He is risen indeed.
>> You look well, master jeweler. I
persevere, your majesty.
>> Yes, you are a wonderful reminder to the
court that our generation is not passed
quite yet. We persevere indeed.
>> I think Fabier had an intimate
relationship with virtually every member
of the imperial family. Their
relationships and their loves, their
passions, [music] their lusts and so on
were expressed through the exchanges of
these gifts. So all of the emotions
which you know are treasured in in them
as these historical figures coalesed
into these fab objects
>> on behalf of his imperial majesty. It is
the great honor of the Carl Faber
company to present this year's Easter
gift.
>> Maria Fodder was [music] unlike Nicholas
II's wife. She had extraordinary charm.
Once she was the Daaja Empress, she was
the most respected member of the [music]
of the royal family. The Daaja was
generally more charming and outgoing
than the Sireina and she had established
a good relationship [music] with Faber.
He had obviously prepared the surprises
very well. She'd always liked them.
Marie Federovna, she was essentially the
same age as him. She was his original
client. She received those original eggs
and there are certainly letters from
her, for example, to her sister [music]
who is our own Queen Alexandra here in
the UK. uh in which she said, "Faber
brought the most wonderful egg. I told
him you're a genius." Clearly, she liked
him. [music]
>> I hopeful majesty is pleased.
>> My dear, dear Faber,
you truly are an unparalleled genius.
>> Faber's connection with [music] the
imperial family was the ultimate cache,
and his workshop was soon producing an
array of items for other European
aristocratic families. He even opened up
an international store in London. That
idea of a feudal society, if it was the
fascination of the court, it quickly
became the fascination of every level of
society. The the aristocracy, the the
traders, [music] the bankers, the
entrepreneurs, they would all want to
participate in that royal fascination.
And it wasn't just in Russia. In
England, exactly the same thing
happened. [music]
>> Fashions such as um cigarette smoking
came to the four. Fabe responded very
quickly to this with cigarette cases.
When you [music] open this, you have not
only the um case itself
and the characteristic [music]
um thumb piece here, it opens to reveal
[music] a signature and a date. So, this
is when a cigarette case is not only a
cigarette case, but it's a case that's
been um [music] purchased by a grand
duchess as a gift.
>> Fab is a Russian company and they were
made [music] in Russia and they are
quintessentially Russian. It does have a
distinct English flavor and I think
there is perhaps more fab within a mile
radius of where we're stood now [music]
than there is in the entirety of Russia
and America put together. Essentially uh
the London shop was started on [music]
the back of commissions or requests for
objects from the British royal family
and the British royal family had learned
[music] to love Faber because of the
relationship between Marie Federova and
Alexandra
>> Edward IIIth [music] and then Queen
Alexander the sister of Maria Federovna
they were also fascinated by Faber
[music] and as a consequence English
society became fascinated by Faber
>> there's a famous story of uh I think he
was by then Edward IIIth being given a
present by a friend saying, "Actually, I
don't particularly want this. If you
want to buy me something, go down to
Faber's shop and look at look at what
he's got."
>> Although the 50 Imperial eggs are
undoubtedly the most desired today,
Faber did make other Easter eggs for
paying customers, including the wealthy
Kelch family. If you were a Russian lady
of some stature, you would have chains
of miniature fab eggs and then there
were eggs in between that were given the
size of hen's eggs and there were
various types which are all marvelous
and they're all wonderful. The problem
with making stuff for the Russian royal
[music] family was the bureaucracy he
had to deal with. He did find it more
cenial making objects for the newly
emerging middle classes or very rich
middle classes I should say. Two very
prominent European families who
commissioned works from Faber were the
Rothschilds and the Nobels for whom the
Nobel ice egg was made. They were happy
to [music] spend what it required, happy
to give him cartlage and and to take
what he made for them and he made some
fabulous objects for them.
>> Faber made two eggs every year during
Nicholas II's reign with the exceptions
of 1904 and 1905 [music] when no eggs
were presented. During this period,
Russia suffered a disastrous defeat in
the Russo-Japanese War. 1905 was an
especially bad year with the bloody
Sunday massacre being carried out in St.
Petersburg and the eventually
unsuccessful 1905 revolution.
Work on the eggs resumed in 1906 [music]
with the Swan Egg with its automatan
miniature. Carl Faber had brought his
son Agathon into the company which now
had over 500 employees. Nefright
exterior. Watercolor miniatures of the
children.
Father,
you can do better.
When World War I broke out in 1914,
Russia was soon dragged in and Zar
Nicholas II left the imperial court to
take charge of the armed forces. In
response, Carl Faber made what would
turn out to be his last Easter gift, the
steel military egg. Presented to the
Zarina Alexandra, it contained a
surprise of her husband and son
commanding the Russian army.
But Nicholas II was never suited to
being a military leader and Russia was
grossly unprepared for the war effort.
Once the Germans came to the help of the
Austrohungarians and pushed the Russian
army back [music] and the soldiers found
they had to go into uh into battle with
no boots, no rifle and were told to take
it off the first corpse they found. Then
the whole thing fell apart. Once
housewives came out of the houses
banging saucepan [music]
because there was no bread then the tsar
had to go.
>> The imperial family were offered an
exile in England [music] but all the
children were ill. They all had measles.
Um and there was also the thought that
the situation wasn't as grave as people
were making out. So they [music] delayed
uh their departure. George V who was a
cousin of the sar took away his offer.
it was considered safer to uh take them
to Siberia.
>> However, the revolutionary Bolevik
forces led by Lenin managed to capture
the Zar, the Zarina and their children
and take them to the city of
Akatarinberg where they came to a
grizzly end.
>> Nikolai Alexandravich, in view of your
relatives continuing attacks on Soviet
Russia, the Eural Executive Committee is
ordered that you are to be executed.
The reason that they were executed was
really because where they were kept in
the eurals, the white army was
approaching and the reds feared perhaps
justified if the whites captured them
again, [music] they would have something
to rally the country around once you got
the tsar back. And I think the panicky
execution was um not due entirely to
sheer brutality but just to deny the the
the opposition in the civil war an
important symbolic figure.
>> There's a certain amount of obfiscation
about it I think because um perhaps
Lenin at various [music] points thought
it wouldn't be good for him to be named
as the killer of the whole family. So
there's also dispute over who gave
orders for the Sar and Sarina to be
killed [music] and who gave orders for
the whole family to be killed.
>> Lenin definitely sanctioned [music] it.
I mean the brutality of the revolution,
the civil war was so horrific that the
deaths of [music] the SARS fit in with
the deaths of millions of others who
were who were shot, tortured, drowned
and so on. The murder of the Russian
royal family meant that KL Faber's life
was hanging in the balance [music] and
his amazing collection of works was in
danger of being lost forever, which
makes the recent rediscovery of one of
his imperial [music] eggs all the more
miraculous.
In July 1918, the Russian royal family
was executed [music] and all their
possessions seized by the new Soviet
state.
Carl Faber, very much a part of the now
extinct Imperial Russia, was in danger
of meeting a similar end.
I saw them once,
the eggs.
I was a boy.
My grandfather took me to your
exhibition.
I'd pestered him about it for weeks.
Did you have a favorite?
>> In the early 1900s, he built a
purpose-built headquarters [music]
in St. Petersburg with the shop on the
ground floor, floors above that included
uh essentially workshops where a lot of
the jewelry happened, although a lot a
lot of the other more specialist work
would happen in other workshops outside.
And then on floors above that, the
design [music] studio.
>> One ruble, 10 copex it cost to get in.
You wouldn't even bend down in the
street to pick that up, would you?
One ruble.
>> I didn't know that was more than he made
in a week.
He was out bloody Sunday.
>> It's estimated that the Faber
Enterprise, well, he had workshops in
St. Petersburg and in Moscow. Moscow was
where they made silver. Uh [music] he
had shops uh in those two places. also
Adessa which was a popular tourist
destination and London which dealt with
most of his [music] international
business uh and total employees either
working for or indirectly for Faber
probably about 1500 at its height.
>> Your friend's imperial guard shot him
right here.
>> He was just an old man.
I wish I'd smashed the eggs when I'd had
the chance.
>> They had a first stage of revolution, a
parliamentary government, but it
couldn't end the war and it couldn't
continue the war. The officers wouldn't
stop fighting. The soldiers wouldn't go
and fight. And finally, a small group of
highly organized men, the Boleviks, uh,
understood how to make a revolution.
>> I wish many things were different.
Comrade Lenin back in exile. You mean
>> bloody Nicholas in his palace?
>> They understood you don't have to
[music] have large numbers. You just
take the railway junction and the
telephone exchange. Once you hold those
two, everyone else is paralyzed. Uh so
you could say it was Lenin's [music]
and Trosky's highly intelligent uh
methods uh for a small group to take
over [music] a large country that that
finished that stage of the revolution.
You're all lutters, war proeteers,
parasites growing fat while the working
man dies.
[panting]
But you don't make the world anymore.
[snorts]
>> [snorts]
>> Time to go, citizen.
Famously, the Bolsheviks arrived at
Faberete's business uh to take it over.
He [music] said, "Just give me a minute
to fetch my hat and coat." And
essentially slipped out the back. Uh
soon afterwards, he was uh smuggled out
of [music] St. Petersburg. Uh he ended
up in Switzerland. uh but he [music] was
clearly broken by the events of the
revolution.
>> He was not placed under arrest nor was
he dragged to Katrineburg and shot or
any of his family members. So um his uh
destiny was very different. Um his
holdings were nationalized and
eventually found his [music] way to
Loausan having traveled with his clothes
and apparently a collection of wine and
died in Lausan in 1920.
>> Faber wasn't the only one who escaped
though. The Daaja Empress also managed
to flee the revolution despite having
been a Zarina herself. She along with
other members of her family were taken
[music] to safety aboard the British
battleship HMS Malbor. George V felt
very guilty when he heard obviously this
terrible tragedy. He made great efforts
to get the Daaja out and [music] that
Sar sister Cassenia and all Cassenia's
children. The local Reds never got round
to executing members of the royal
family. They were too much of a hurry
defending themselves and so she managed
to get out on a British battleship
>> on the Mulra. Prince Felix Yusupov
[music]
who murdered Rasbutin had two Rembrandts
and he was seen on deck with them rolled
up under his arm. Uh there was the Faber
egg, the cross of St. George down in the
hold. And the Yupus puffs also had other
treasures. 20 million pounds worth of
[music] um jewels and treasures on on
board. So quite an extraordinary amount.
The cross of St. George egg was the last
Faber egg presented to the Daaja
Empress. By taking it with her, it
became the only imperial Easter egg
known to have left Russia with its
owner. Carl Faber [music] may have
escaped to Switzerland, but his son
Agathon, who'd become a key part of the
Faber company, was not so lucky and
remained in the now Soviet Russia. I
think a lot of the enterprise [music]
and dealing within Faber's world was
conducted by Agathon and I think he did
exactly the same [music] after the
revolution as he had done before and he
was a conduit himself for the movement
of objects out of Russia to the west.
And in fact [music] in Wartsky's ledgers
there are um references to us buying
objects from Faber and the Fabe was
Agathon Fabe.
>> Agathon Faber managed to escape Soviet
Russia himself in 1927 but he had left
behind one of the unfinished eggs due to
be given to the Romanoffs in 1917.
>> It was found essentially [music] in the
Fursman Minological Museum in Moscow.
They thought it was a lampstand. It is
actually [music] an egg-shaped bit of
polished blue glass on a funny sort of
cloud-shaped uh bit of [music] other
glass. Uh they now know in fact that
that was going to be the egg for
Alexander Federovna. The story of the
blue Zarovich constellation egg reveals
the precarious times that faced the
imperial treasures after the Russian
Revolution. Both Lenin and Stalin
authorized the sale of many of Russia's
greatest works of art to fund the Soviet
programs.
The revolution brought the Bolsheviks to
power. Uh even if there hadn't been
economic collapse as well, it would have
changed everything. Uh economic collapse
as well just made it all even worse.
>> There was so much Russian art and you
could argue that in fact Russia had
plundered all of Europe in the 18th
[music] century. Katherine the Great got
an enormous amount of of stuff from
impoverished English collectors and
aristocrats.
>> One of Lenin's famous commands was loot
the lutters. That is to say, all these
people who have been uh living uh the
life of Riley for the last uh 50, 100,
300 years, [music]
uh it is now our turn to loot them.
Despite the looting, the smashing,
[music] uh the rotting away. Uh there's
still the Hermitage Gallery in St.
Petersburg can only display a tiny
fraction of what it has. [music]
>> Countless works of art were sold abroad,
including the Faber eggs, and their
buyers were a very mysterious bunch.
They included Emanuel Snowman of Watsky
and Armond Hammer of accidental
petroleum.
>> Armed Hammer is a fascinating character
and he was almost the Joseph Deine of
his day.
>> Multi-millionaire capitalist who alleges
that he is in fact a communist um and
then goes over and makes big deals with
with Lenin.
>> He was not a communist. He was a
capitalist through and through. He
organized uh trunk shows through uh
department stores [music] across America
and catered to the way that women bought
things [music] and made uh fab pieces
accessible to uh the American public.
>> Ultimately he became the agent for the
sale [snorts] of Russian works of art
primarily almost solely to America and
so he was the conduit from Russia
[music] to America whilst Emanuel
Snowman was a conduit from Russia to
Western Europe. A king's ransom in art
jewels. Gems from the collection of the
late Zar of Russia on exhibition.
Treasure worth many millions procured
from the Soviet government after the
revolution.
>> Arand Hammer and Emanuel Snowman were
two of the major figures who had
facilitated the movement of Faber eggs
to the west. But one man who wanted to
[music] gather them for himself was
Malcolm Forbes of Forbes magazine. He
went on a spending spree. Malcolm Forbes
was a relative late come and Forbes was
possessed [music] by a collecting mania.
>> He was an obsessive collector and I
suppose um the great thing about um
Faber eggs is there only what 50
Imperial ones and another [music] 16. So
you could you you could actually get the
lot. It was one of those things where
you could find you had the complete
stamp [music] collection.
>> In a span of two decades, Malcolm Forbes
managed to [music] get his hands on nine
imperial fab eggs in total. His ambition
was always [music] to have more Easter
eggs in the Kremlin. He never quite got
there, but he got very close.
>> While most of the Imperial Faber eggs
were sold abroad for foreign currency,
10 did remain in the Kremlin armory and
have never [music] left the country.
>> And one of the great sort of stories and
unknowns of these eggs is that we know
exactly where they were in Soviet times,
[music] we know where they were in
imperial times, and we really know where
they were once they emerged in the West.
the scald duggery and the mischief of
those original and first transactions.
[music] We don't know. And so I feel as
though there are wonderfully sort of
untold stories there involving these
sort of ravenous dealers and sort of
mischievous individuals. Malcolm Forb's
determination to collect as many Faber
eggs as he could helped shoot up the
price of these one-of-a-kind treasures.
When the winter egg went on sale in
2002, [music]
it was bought by a Qatari bidder for
$8.7 million. All done at $8,700,000.
Maria, your bit.
>> My favorite egg is [music] one that was
given to Marie Federovna in 1913. Uh,
and that's one of the most striking
things about it is here we are almost 30
years after that first egg and you're
still getting wonderful creativity. It
looks like you're looking through a
winter fog [music] as you look through
the egg. Uh, it's sitting on more carved
rock crystal which is polished so much
that it looks like melting ice. And then
within the egg, so you can see it
through a winter fog or open the egg and
lift it out, there's a little basket of
enamel [music] flowers of spring and
enemies. So you've got a wonderful
symbolism there of spring seen through
winter.
>> In 2004 [music] though, Malcolm Forb's
collection of Faber eggs would make
their way back home to St. Petersburg
when they were purchased by the Russian
oligarch Victor Vexelberg. Vexelbeck
[music] I think spent something like
hund00 million dollars getting uh quite
a large number of eggs back.
>> They've gone back to the um the Faber
Museum in St. Petersburg which actually
is a fabulous destination for them.
Whatever the mechanism of why they got
there where they have ended up is
[music] the perfect home for them.
>> For the longest time 42 Imperial Faber
eggs were known to [music] have survived
the Russian Revolution with just eight
remaining lost. But then out of the
blue, an [music] American man arrived at
Wartsky in London with evidence that one
of those eggs had been found.
Wartsky in London is forever entwined
with the history of Faber. So it's the
[music] only place you would go if you
thought you'd found a missing Imperial
Faber egg. And that's exactly what an
American individual recently did in
walked a gentleman. [music]
And he was the most unassuming,
unprepossessing individual. He was
wearing a plaid American shirt, the
quintessential red plaid American shirt,
jeans. He asked me by name, and when I
came up, he couldn't actually speak to
me. His mouth was dry with fear. There
was a sort of like a like a sort of
inability to communicate. Just a couple
of years before, a pair of intrepid
researchers looked through a 1964
catalog of the auctioneers Parker
Bernet, now a part of Sures. Within it,
they discovered an image of the missing
third imperial fab egg, which had been
sold with everyone unaware of its true
origin. The only other known image of
this egg is from the 1902 von Dervvis
Mansion exhibition, where many of the
Faber eggs had been displayed. But this
new discovery proved that the egg had
made it to the west and there was now a
far clearer photograph of it.
Kieran McCarthy of Watsky was part of an
article published by the Daily Telegraph
on this catalog discovery which gave
some hope that the egg may turn up
someday [music] now that it was proved
to have survived the Russian Revolution.
But little did he know how quickly that
article would [music] lead him to the
egg itself.
I went out to America as pretty much as
quickly as my feet and the wings would
carry me afterwards. We traveled a long
way to a very remote part and I walked
into the kitchen of this house which is
a million miles from Imperial St.
Petersburg and sat on a kitchen counter
there was um a cupcake and next to it
the uh the missing Easter egg.
>> A Google search had proved key in
bringing owner and expert together. He
had no idea whatsoever that it was
Faber. He had no concept that [music]
this was a missing imperial egg. And so
he typed into Google of all things. He
typed Vashron and Constantine [music]
and egg. What came up was all of the art
historical research which I and Wartsky
had been involved in surrounding this
egg. And so although the miracle of him
walking through our door one day was a
miracle, the actual link and the reason
why he walked [music] through our door
was that research.
>> It proves that these eggs are out there
to find. You know, there were 50 eggs.
Some of them were [music] destroyed or
uh melted down or disappeared. And uh we
had thought that eight were missing and
until recently [music] uh that was the
case and then this this this third egg
um appeared.
>> Well, the egg displays every wonder of
Faber's work. The first is it's a very
simple construction. It's a readed gold
egg, but the simplicity belies how
difficult it is to make. Each one of
these reads is formed by hand by a
craftsman at a workbench. They taper at
the same rate to an exact point both at
the bottom and at the top. And when you
press the diamond at the front, it opens
to reveal the watch by Vasher and
Constantine. And this scrolling around
the bezel [music] of the aperture where
it's there is found on many of them.
It's the identical engravings on Cradle
with Garland's egg. And so you begin to
see these little sort of hints of what
Fabier has done before and of how
Faber's craftsman worked. And another
aspect is when you flip the watch up, it
sits which is a beautiful little piece
of design which actually allows it to
work as not just an Easter egg but as a
clock. And where you really see the
absolute to force of gold smithing is
not so much in the simple egg but in the
far more elaborate stand. four colored
gold roses and roses are an emblem of
love and so the Zar and the Zarina when
they saw this would know that it was an
expression of love and then the lion paw
feet they're beautifully finished on top
and they are slightly stylized but very
sort of endearing lion's paws that when
you turn it over and look at the base
the pads and the underside of the feet
are as beautifully represented and of
course the zarini would never have seen
that because it would have sat like
that. This is one of the most
sophisticated pieces of goldsmithing
from Faberes or anybody else's hands
that has ever been created and it would
have been a gift appropriate for us. But
what of the seven Imperial Faber eggs
that are still missing? Well, one of
them [music] is called the Cherub with
chariot egg, and it could be seen in the
same photograph from the 1902 Vonervis
exhibition that featured the third
imperial egg. Sitting sneakily behind
the caucus' egg, you can see the wheel
of the cherub with chariot egg and can
catch a glimpse of it in the reflection
of the glass casing.
This artist's interpretation shows what
the egg could look like if you happen to
notice another 20 million pound treasure
at an antique store. But this isn't the
only Faber egg of which we have but a
faint glimpse. The fifth egg in the
series is known as the Nessair egg and
it featured at a 1949 exhibition of
Faber eggs in London.
>> London and a region street dwellers
becomes the setting for an exhibition of
the work of Carl Faber that great
craftsman of Zaris Russia. His son Euene
Fabge holds one of the jewelstudied
enamel and gold Easter eggs made for the
last empress as a gift from the Zar.
Kieran McCarthy, who [music] was
instrumental in finding the third Faber
egg, has also brought us closer to
uncovering this one when he found an
image of it in the back of a photograph
[music] taken at the exhibition. That's
one of the most frustrating sort of
events in my life. Watsky is an
Edwardian company and our ledgers are
arranged and on the left hand side it
shows what the object is. And I looked
across where [music] we have the name of
the buyer, the address of the buyer and
how much they paid. So I thought if Mr.
blogs lives [music] at four blogs
square. I can go knock on four blogs
square and find the egg within. But I
look across and it [music] said a
stranger and and Wartsky's discretion as
it is with this egg. We cannot reveal
who bought or sold this egg and there is
no way of telling where it went.
>> The exquisite work of the man who was
caught jeweler and goldmith to Russia's
royal house still mirrors the splendor
of an age that is no more. Although the
necessary egg featured at this
exhibition, it was not known at the time
to be the fifth imperial Easter egg. The
necessary egg was never recognized as
Imperial Fab, but importantly it was
recognized as a Faber egg. So [music]
this egg here was never known to be
Faber and so because of that it was
never likely to be saved because it was
fab and as a result this danced on the
precipice of the melting pot over and
over again. It was [music] sold to
almost certainly an English customer and
it was only in 1952. So it is likely to
have survived and that one I I feel in
my instinct has [music] survived. Of the
five eggs where where we've got no trace
of them coming to the west. It's
possible that they'll emerge one day.
It's equally possible that they were
destroyed in the whole chaos around the
revolution.
Despite the slim chances of discovery,
there are photos of two of these five
most elusive Faber eggs. The 1909
Alexander III [music] commemorative egg
and the 1903 Royal Danish egg. Oddly, we
also have the surprise of the 1897 Mauve
egg, but not the egg itself. The missing
royal Danish egg is the intriguing one,
though, as it was presented to the Daaja
Empress whilst she was away at her
original home of Copenhagen in 1903.
It's not known for sure if she ever
brought the egg back to Russia. So, it
may be the case that something is a miss
in the state of Denmark.
You just never know. And that's partly
the mystery of them. And I think that's
why this one, this particular [music]
egg, is so significant because it is one
of the missing ones.
>> Well, it seems possible that it might be
there. Um she [music] she wasn't very
keen to pass anything on when she was
alive and she used to say you can have
my treasure when I'm dead. So uh yeah it
could be. Yes.
>> When you know the history it becomes
rather blas you know. Oh I know that
one. I've seen it there. It [music] was
exhibited there and it went there and
they paid so much and they did this.
It's the ones you don't know about that
actually excite the um the mind and the
fascination. All seven of the missing
eggs are ones that were presented to the
Daaja Empress Marie Fiorodnner. It's
known that she escaped Russia on the HMS
Morbra with the cross of St. George egg
on board.
>> The Daaja took the egg with her
presumably to England. I think uh then
[music]
Senia, her daughter, then Vasili, her
youngest son, [music] ended up with it
and then he sold it.
>> But there's no reason why this should
have been the only egg she took with
her. It's possible she packed up the
empire nefright egg and mauve egg or any
other of the missing ones such as the
second hen egg with sapphire pendant.
These are the only three eggs left of
which we have no images. But that
doesn't mean they're not out there.
>> It's like James Dean. It's like, you
know, if if they if carried on and we
were now on the 142nd Faber egg, I think
they would not have the same appeal. But
the fact that it's finite, the the glory
of Faber is that it is no more. The
reason we've all heard of Faber today is
because of the eggs. These great,
fabulous objects that he started to make
for the Russian royal family. They are
just so over the top, so wonderful, so
inspired in their creativity as well.
They're just wonderful objects [music]
uh for combining history and
craftsmanship. The extraordinary about
Fabes, the very very expensive materials
used, unique jewels, the the materials
themselves are a wealth beyond
imagination. Then the extraordinary
craftsmanship, the miniaturization of
the [music] work. It's an oriental type
of work. It's very very Iranian Indian
uh in in its use of [music] jewelry.
It's the intricacy.
>> Fab eggs sort of encapsulate the romance
of the of the story. So much um care
[music] gone into them.
>> They're a product of the social,
cultural, financial, political
circumstances of that moment. [music]
And it's that collision of great
craftsmanship and uncompromising
patronage that gives rise to this
fascination with fabric.
Oh,
heat, heat.